Guide to the New-York Historical Society General Correspondence 1805-2024 (bulk, 1805-1982) NYHS-RG 2
New-York Historical Society
- Series IV. General Correspondence, 1908-1982; 117.29 Linear feet in 282 document boxes and one oversize folder
  - Correspondence 1908-1926. Co (8 folders), 1908-1923 (Box 84, Folder 1-8)
    Includes extensive correspondence of frequent donor J. Ackerman Coles and John Cox Jr.(Joint Committee on Records of the Religious Society of Friends); materials relating to the bequests of J. Marcus Boorman and Maria Duane Bleecker Cox. Correspondents: Colonial Dames of the State of New York, Columbia County Historical Society, John G. Coyle, Rev. John Cornell and various departments and representatives of Columbia University, Cornell University, and U.S. Congress (including Library of Congress). Subjects: Memorial museum on Constitution Island.
  - Correspondence 1908-1926. Co (5 folders), 1924-1926 (Box 85, Folder 1-5)
    Includes extensive correspondence of frequent donor J. Ackerman Coles; inventory of materials presented by Isabella Vache Cox and Mary E. Cox; letters concerning the bequest of a desk bookcase formerly owned by Colonel Henry Rutgers by Katharine Rutgers Lane; H.M. Cordell from office of Henry Ford, concerning the dating of lights in N-YHS collections. Subjects: New-York Historical Society Scholarship historical essay competition in collaboration with Henry J. Carman of Columbia University; see also New-York Historical Society Scholarship essay submissions, NYHS-RG 13.
  - Correspondence 1908-1926. Cr - Cy (6 folders), 1908-1922 (Box 85, Folder 6-11)
    Correspondents: N-YHS treasurer Warren C. Crane, John D. Crimmins, and David E. Cronin. Frequent correspondents include R. Fulton Cutting, (Mrs.) W. Bayard Cutting, Cyclone Fence Company, and the William T. Palmer & Company, Inc.
  - Correspondence 1908-1926. Da (6 folders) (Box 86, Folder 1-6)
    Dominated by historian Gherardi B. Davis. Also includes ephemera and correspondence from Daughters of the Holland Dames, Daughters of the Revolution, Daughters of the Cincinnati, Dayton Art Institute; 1925 letter from J. Clarence Davies suggesting that the Museum of the City of New York is duplicating the efforts of N-YHS and wasting city and taxpayer money; packet of materials on Davey Reorganization Bill supplied by Congressional Rep. Martin L. Davey himself; illustration of undated Georgina pre-revolutionary house, drawn by Smith Birdsey Dayton.
  - Correspondence 1908-1926. De (3 folders), 1908-1915 (Box 86, Folder 7-9)
    Correspondents: Philip Schuyler de Luze, John Ross Delafield, Joseph L. Delafield, and Mary L. Dey.
  - Correspondence 1908-1926. De (6 folders), 1916-1926 (Box 87, Folder 1-6)
    Includes Henry F. De Puit discussions of N-YHS "going public" and reorganization of Executive Committee; lecturers Theodore De Booy and Emeterio de La Garza Jr.; Grace Schuyler de Luze donation of four-post bed and other family heirlooms; Richard and John Ross Delafield proposal of donation for Delafield Family room; 1925 N-YHS circular of information; two drafts of undated manuscript written by son of Frederic de Peyster.
  - Correspondence 1908-1926. Di (2 folders) (Box 87, Folder 7-8)
    Includes Charles A. Ditmas and his campaign for commemoration of the Battle of Long Island. Correspondents: H.W. Dickinson and Harriet C. Dickinson.
  - Correspondence 1908-1926. Do - Dy (2 folders), 1908-1915 (Box 87, Folder 9-10)
    Includes 1812 bookplate belonging to John Turner and materials relating to bequests of William J. Dodd and Frederic D. Durand.
  - Correspondence 1908-1926. Do - Dy (5 folders), 1916-1926 (Box 88, Folder 1-5)
    Includes materials relating to the bequest of Frederic D. Durand, Mary S. Durrell, David Stuart Dodge; extensive inventory of sheet music, New York City scene prints, and other local and state-related items held by J. Francis Driscoll; Robert E. Dowling on involvement in honor ceremony for I.N. Phelps Stokes. Correspondents: Henry Russell Drowne.
  - Correspondence 1908-1926. E (3 folders), 1908-1918 (Box 88, Folder 6-8)
    Includes ephemera for the Evangelistic Committee of New York City.
  - Correspondence 1908-1926. E (5 folders), 1919-1926 (Box 89, Folder 1-5)
    Includes acquisition inquiries from private collectors of Egyptian antiquities; correspondence with Empire Wrecking Co. regarding the retrieval of a bas relief, box in the cornerstone, and other items from former N-YHS Second Avenue building prior to its demolition; undated copy of the will of William Banks Gilley. Correspondents: William Webster Ellsworth, Essex Institute, Harold L. Ehrich, George Simpson Eddy, Erie Centennial Commission, George S. Eddy, Egypt Exploration Society.
  - Correspondence 1908-1926. Wilberforce Eames (Box 89, Folder 6)
    Comprised of various reference exchanges with the head of the American History Division, New York Public Library. (See also: "New York City" folders, where much New York Public Library correspondence, including Eames, is filed.)
  - Correspondence 1908-1926. Fa (2 folders) (Box 89, Folder 7-8)
    Correspondents: John Truitt Farrell, Fairfield County Historical Society, W.R. Farrell, De Witt Clinton Falls, Charles R. Faruolo (mortgage payments for property at 424 East 11th Street).
  - Correspondence 1908-1926. Helen Lincklaen Fairchild (4 folders) (Box 90, Folder 1-4)
    Communications with scholar and N-YHS benefactor, chiefly centered around research into her Forman and Ledyard family ancestry, and donation of materials, many related to Francis Adrian Van der Kemp. Includes clipping of her New York Times "Letter to the Editor" defending the Society. [Alternative name: Mrs. Charles S. Fairchild.]
  - Correspondence 1908-1926. Fe (2 folders) (Box 90, Folder 5-6)
    Correspondents: J.L.G. Ferris, David Ferguson, Mrs. Morris P. Ferris.
  - Correspondence 1908-1926. Fi (3 folders) (Box 90, Folder 7-9)
    Correspondents: DeLancey W. Fisk, D. Havelock Fisher, Filson Club (Louisville, KY), Field Museum, Committee for the Protection of the Park Section of Fifth Avenue and Fifth Avenue Association.
  - Correspondence 1908-1926. Stuyvesant Fish (3 folders), 1910-1926 (Box 91, Folder 1-3)
    Documents Fish's research inquiries with N-YHS librarians and activities as Recording Secretary (elected in 1917). Includes discussion of difficulties obtaining alcohol used in conservation treatment during Prohibition; response to complaint by Virginia H. Field about the society's decision to open to the public on Sunday, the Sabbath Day; letter from Emlen Hare Miller referencing his request of Fish to investigate N-YHS affairs; Publication Fund share transfers. Subjects: Gen. John Lamb, Gramercy Park, Beverly Robinson House, Nicholas Fish (military career), Proclamation of Governor Benjamin Fletcher (1693), Continental Village.
  - Correspondence 1908-1926. Fl - Fo (5 folders) (Box 91, Folder 4-8)
    Includes menu for 1923 anniversary dinner, catered by Fowler; survey and responses to investigation into activities, operations, and funding of major historical societies, forwarded by Dixon Ryan Fox; receipts from technical photographer R.B. Fleming; letter to Henry C. Folger proposing the construction of rooms to house his famed Shakespeare collection at N-YHS [see also: "James B. Wilbur" folder]. Correspondents: New York Fourth of July Committee, Joseph H. Foster, Flower Memorial Library, Worthington C. Ford, B. Sherman Fowler, Ford Educational Film Libraries, Dixon Ryan Fox.
  - Correspondence 1908-1926. Fr - Fu (7 folders) (Box 92, Folder 1-7)
    Includes extensive correspondence with prominent genealogist Josephine C. Frost; and explorer Charles W. Furlong (also: lecture circulars); distribution materials for public appeal for Benjamin Franklin birthday celebration; New York Press clipping on Henry Frank and Independent Liberal Congregation (November 21, 1909); suggestion by Annie Wilson France to collect African-American traditional (slave?) songs overheard at Brooklyn's Home for Aged Colored People. Correspondents: Robert Fridenberg, Helen C. Frick, Frick Art Reference Library, and organizations based in France.
  - Correspondence 1908-1926. Ga (3 folders) (Box 92, Folder 8-11)
    Correspondents: Charles Carroll Gardner (incuding letterpress pamphlet advertising genealogy services), Charles Gaffin; Mr. and Mrs. R. Horace (see also: individual folder), Albert, and other Gallatin family members, generally inquiries about the Gallatin Papers.
  - Correspondence 1908-1926. R. Horace Gallatin (2 folders), 1917-1926 (Box 93, Folder 1-2)
    Documents activity as N-YHS Treasurer (1920-1928), including oversight of mortgages and E.A. Hoffman, G.W. Van Slyck, and De Peyster funds.
  - Correspondence 1908-1926. Ge - Gi (5 folders) (Box 93, Folder 3-7)
    Includes report "Defects In the Heating & Ventilation System" conducted by R.P. Bolton Company and proposal and repair estimates from Gillis & Geoghegan; materials relating to the estates of Mary S. Durrell and Annie Loucks Gebhard; bills and correspondence from frequent service providers Jacob Gescheidt & Co. and photographic supplier G. Gennert. Correspondents: Stephen W. Giles, Henry J. Gensler, General Theological Seminary, Joseph B. Gilder, and individuals and organizations based in Georgia. Subjects: Gerritsen Basin Park.
  - Correspondence 1908-1926. Gl - Go (3 folders) (Box 93, Folder 8-10)
    Includes offer for 2nd Avenue building by Arthur Goldstein on behalf of Louis Minsky; EJ Goodspeed inquiries on the Abbott Egyptian Collection; tickets for Mrs. Frederic S. Goodwin lectures on Mexico at various venues and dedication of Joan of Arc statue in Central Park; extensive dealings with Globe Indemnity Company (elevator certification, workmen's compensation, bond on behalf of Edward Steers) and Goodspeed's Book Shop; letter from Glenn Gould criticizing treatment of Mrs. Van Rensselaer and member behavior at meeting.
  - Correspondence 1908-1926. Gr - Gu ( 7 folders) (Box 94, Folder 1-7)
    Includes letters and later bequest of Isaac J. Greenwood (dispersal of personal library managed by daughter Eliza Rudd Greenwood); librarian's letter to Henry E. Gregory describing the Van Rensselaer-led attack; distribution materials from the Gypsy Lore Society; correspondence with newly formed Greenwich Village Historical Society (variety of ephemera, birthday card and expression of fealty to N-YHS, signed by officers and members); Grosvenor Library (objection to Librarian Augustus H. Shearer's negative report on historical societies); and Rocellus S. Guernsey's certificate of election to honorary member of the American Scenic and Historic Preservation Society. Correspondents: Langdon Greenwood, Mrs. Edward Green, Grolier Club, I.S. Graves, Guttag Bros.
  - Correspondence 1908-1926. Ha (2 folders) (Box 94, Folder 8-9)
    Correspondents: Emily C. Hawley.
  - Correspondence 1908-1926. Ha (9 folders), 1912-1926 (Box 95, Folder 1-9)
    Includes permission to Church of the Divine Paternity to cultivate land on the 76th street corner of N-YHS property; letters from supportive members following Van Rensselaer attack and McDougall Hawkes suggesting N-YHS loan objects outside its scope to more appropriate institutions, particularly "these mummified bulls, etc., which are a constant source of ridicule when associated with an Historical Society of New York; it is unfortunate to overlook a public sense of humor." Correspondents: Charles T. Harback, Lathrop C. Harper, Oscar W. Hamilton, H.O. Hart, John H. Hazelton, James S. Hall, Charles Henry Hart, Edward Hagman Hall, Richard T.H. Halsey, Robert H. Hatch, Harvard College, Harvard University, and organizations associated with the neighborhood of Harlem.
  - Correspondence 1908-1926. He (5 folders) (Box 96, Folder 1-5)
    Includes materials relating to the bequest of Caroline M. Hertzell; calendar reform bill (in Spanish) sent by Carlos A. Hesse. Correspondents: A.G.(?) Heaton, Victoria Hewitt, Charles F. Heartman.
  - Correspondence 1908-1926. Hi (5 folders) (Box 96, Folder 6-10)
    Includes donations and Assistant Librarian application package from William A. Hildebrand of the Dramatic Morgue and Typographical Library and Museum; ephemera from Hispanic Society of America and Conference of Historical Societies. Correspondents: Executive Committee member Frederick Trevor Hill, C.G. Hine, Frederick S. Hills (Argus Company), Frederick H. Hitchcock.
  - Correspondence 1908-1926. Ho (8 folders) (Box 97, Folder 1-8)
    Includes extensive correspondence with editor Thomas W. Hotchkiss and Paul W. Hoffman, from hired work on Egyptian Collections through subsequent employment and financial problems; copy of statement of gratitude for the "Divine Being" protecting NYC Mayor William Jay Gaynor upon the anniversary of his assassination attempt; photographs supplied and captioned by Arthur P. Howard of burial places, tombstones, and monuments (John Laurens, William Heath[?]); the Holland Society on adoption of new city flag and seal; exchanges with photo-stat service provider E.S. Holland (and efforts to secure necessary machinery due to war rationing, ultimately loaned by U.S. Shipping Board Emergency Fleet Corporation); documents relating to the bequest of Ella N. Holgate; regular ice cream orders to J.M. Horton. Correspondents: C.A. Hoppin, John J. Hopper, W.P. Horton, Houghton Mifflin Company, The Hague (Holland).
  - Correspondence 1908-1926. Roswell Randall Hoes, 1908-1931 (Box 97, Folder 9)
    Documents numerous reference requests, chiefly centered around Hoes's editing of As I Remember Recollections of American Society during the Nineteenth Century by Marian Gouverneur and further Ulster County and Gouverneur family genealogical research, photostatting of Hoes's original copy of the 1800 Ulster County Gazette, and discussions with his widow Rose Gouverneur Hoes regarding the deposit of materials, following his death in 1922 (which were ultimately transferred, according to the original terms, to the Senate House Association of Kingston in 1930).
  - Correspondence 1908-1926. Samuel V. Hoffman (3 folders) (Box 98, Folder 1-3)
    Documents Hoffman's N-YHS presidency (1903-1912), subsequent convalescence, Executive Commitee membership (1919-1937) and further committee work, acquisitions, donations, and special event participation. Includes discussions of advances of funds to the society; oversight of facilities; establishment of Susan M. Watson binding fund; relationship and fallout with Henry Dexter as well as his bequest to N-YHS; health and deaths of prominent members and colleagues; omission of several female patrons from 1908 annual report; unspecified cataloging work following retirement; updates on Society activity from the Librarian; and the Van Rensselaer episode (or, "this season of female complaints"). Other items: blank photograph request form and 1913 meeting resolution honoring Hoffman upon his resignation.
  - Correspondence 1908-1926. Samuel V. Hoffman. Bills (6 folders), 1908-1916; 1930-1932 (Box 98, Folder 4-9)
    Annotated list of gifts of S.V. Hoffman between 1903 and 1912 and receipts for goods and services purchased by Hoffman for N-YHS, as an advance or gift, between 1917 and 1932.
  - Correspondence 1908-1926. Hu (4 folders) (Box 98, Folder 10-13)
    Includes materials relating to the estate of James B. Ludlow. Correspondents: Richard M. Hurd, Charles R. Huntington, Elmer T. Hutchinson, Mrs. W.D. Hurlbutt, Historical Society of Hudson County, Hunts Point Community League, Hunter College, and various Huguenot associations.
  - Correspondence 1908-1926. Huntington (2 folders) (Box 99, Folder 1-2)
    Includes Archer Milton Huntington (Foreign Corresponding Secretary) and the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery (librarians George Watson Cole and Leslie M. Bliss); other Huntingtons in proceeding "Hu" folders.
  - Correspondence 1908-1926. Hy (Box 99, Folder 3)
    Correspondents: Henry St. John Hyde and James H. Hyde.
  - Correspondence 1908-1926. I (3 folders) (Box 99, Folder 4-6)
    Includes reproduction of portrait of Washington Irving around the age of 30, a 1925 price confirmation from Independent Movie Supply Company to equip N-YHS auditorium with projector, and illustrated marketing brochure from the Imperial Brush Company (1917).Correspondents: Charles Isham, William M. Ivins, George Iles, Dr. Frederucj Usrawk [in German], International Film Service, and various organizations based in Iowa, Illinois, Indiana, annd those with names beginning with International
  - Correspondence 1908-1926. Ja - Je (2 folders), 1908-1919 (Box 99, Folder 7-8)
    Correspondents: E.C. Jameson, Emily Jackson, Charles H. Jackson, J. Franklin Jameson (Carnegie Institution of Washington and "Writings on American History").
  - Correspondence 1908-1926. Ja - Je (3 folders), 1920-1926 (Box 100, Folder 1-3)
    Includes exchange with J. Franklin Jameson on western and state-funded historical societies. Correspondents: Arthur Curtiss James, Walter Jennings, Le Roy Jeffers (the Associated Mountaineering Clubs of North America), Charles F. Jenkins, Thomas Jefferson Memorial Foundation. Subjects: Edwin Smith medical papyrus in Egyptian Collection.
  - Correspondence 1908-1926. Jo - Ju (6 folders), 1920-1926 (Box 100, Folder 4-9)
    Includes attempted acquisition of John Pintard papers from Harris H. Johnston; proposal for building fundraising by John Price Jones Corporation (plus report of progress on publicity campaign for the American Antiquarian Society); distribution materials for motion picture theatre equipment; list of "Negroes Writing Before the Civil War;" ephemera for the unveiling of the Joan of Arc statue on Riverside Drive. Correspondents: H.P. Johnston, John J. Judge, John White Johnston, C.K. Johnson, J.H. Jordan, John Jermain Memorial Library, Johns Hopkins University, John Carter Brown Library (Brown University).
  - Correspondence 1908-1926. Joint Committee of Printing, U.S. Congress (7 folders), 1925-1926; 1928 (Box 101, Folder 1-7)
    Includes drafted entries for the Biographical Congressional Directory formally submitted to the N-YHS librarian for fact-checking; packets for 1925 Congressional bills H.R. 4795 and H.R. 4798, submitted by Martin L. Davey, advocate for reorganization of the government.
  - Correspondence 1908-1926. Ka - Ke (5 folders) (Box 102, Folder 1-5)
    Includes 1921 resignation of Librarian Robert Kelby on basis of poor health and other related communications; postcards sent by R.H. Kelly to James Benedict from Europe in 1914. Correspondents: Frank Berger Kelley (City History Club of New York), Austin Baxter Keep, Daniel Edwards Kennedy, Gouverneur Kemble, Jennie E. Kent, John Keller, Kansas State Historical Society and Kentucky State Historical Society.
  - Correspondence 1908-1926. Ki (3 folders) (Box 102, Folder 6-8)
    Includes ephemera and correspondence from Kings County Historical Society (President Charles A. Ditmas); inquiry for prints of Central Park from Theodore Kimball of Olmsted Brothers; hand-illustrated letters addressed to "Addie" from artist W. Ruloff Kip, recounting his discovery of the Society and interest in employment with the Egyptian collections. Correspondents: Edwin P. Kilroe.
  - Correspondence 1908-1926. Kl - Ky, 1906-1916 (Box 102, Folder 9)
    Correspondents: de Lancey Kountze.
  - Correspondence 1908-1926. Kl - Ky (2 folders), 1917-1926 (Box 103, Folder 1-2)
    Includes George F. Kunz (Authors Club) addressing criticism that Society does not "do something of a more public character" and appointment to represent N-YHS in opposition to the destruction of the High Bridge. Correspondents: de Lancey Kountze.
  - Correspondence 1908-1926. La (5 folders) (Box 103, Folder 3-7)
    Includes materials relating to the estates of Daniel Parrish (represented by Charles H. Larence) and Katharine Rutgers Conger Lane; print request from Ladies Home Journal to accompany article by Mrs. John King Van Rensselaer on the Peter Marie miniature collection. Correspondents: John D. Lawson, Lancaster County Historical Society, Algot Lange, Henry W. Lanier, Charles R. Lamb (Battery Park Liberty Pole).
  - Correspondence 1908-1926. Bella C. Landauer, 1923-1926 (Box 103, Folder 8)
    Documents Landauer's application for life membership, personal ephemera collection development, and donation of bookplates to the Society.
  - Correspondence 1908-1926. Lawyers Mortgage Company (2 folders), 1908-1926; 1928 (Box 103, Folder 9-10)
    Includes mortgage certificates and renewals, interest payment receipts, and related correspondence.
  - Correspondence 1908-1926. Le (4 folders) (Box 104, Folder 1-4)
    Includes postcards from Tilda Lent. Correspondents: John Thomas Lee, Lenox Library, Lewis Historical Publishing Company, A.R. Ledoux, Mark Levy.
  - Correspondence 1908-1926. Charles M. Lefferts, 1909, 1914-1924 (Box 104, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence 1908-1926. Li (4 folders), 1908-1922 (Box 104, Folder 6-9)
    Includes annotated copy of Library of Congress duplicate newspaper copies available for exchange; bills and associated planning for installation of book stacks and manuscript cases, in addition to various supply orders, with Library Bureau, and bookbinding and printing with J.J. Little & Ives Company; copy of Alexander J. Wall deposition in legal dispute with Trow; Printing & Bookbinding Company regarding the proofs and plates for N-YHS catalogs. Correspondents: James M. Lincoln, bookseller George Emery Littlefield, Library of Congress, Libman Contracting Company, John Thomas Lee, Lenox Library, Lewis Historical Publishing Company.
  - Correspondence 1908-1926. Li (4 folders), 1923-1926 (Box 105, Folder 1-4)
    Correspondents: J.J. Little & Ives Company and Library of Congress.
  - Correspondence 1908-1926. Lj - Lo (3 folders) (Box 105, Folder 5-7)
    Includes correspondence with patron Le Duc de Loubat, contributor of $20,000 to the Building Fund; ephemera and communications from Louisiana Historical Society, Long Island Historical Society (librarian: Emma Toedteberg), and Lower Wall Street Business Men's Association; materials relating to the bequest of J. Marcus Boorman. Correspondents: Percival Hall Lombard, various organizations and companies based in London, Los Angeles, and Louisiana. Subjects: University of Louvain.
  - Correspondence 1908-1926. Lu - Ly (2 folders) (Box 105, Folder 8-9)
    Correspondents: James B. Ludlow, Le Lyceum Societe des Femme de France a New York, Lynn Historical Society. Subjects: Lusitania memorial service.
  - Correspondence 1908-1926. Mc - Mac (8 folders) (Box 106, Folder 1-8)
    Includes numerous reference inquiries by William M. MacBean and Byron McCandless (history of flags); illustrated profile of Margaret Crooke Inglis of Ulster County (mounted print of original drawing, circa 1777, submitted by frequent correspondent Ross McCord). Correspondents: W.G. MacFarlane, MacMillian Company, Alice Howland Macomber.
  - Correspondence 1908-1926. Ma (11 folders) (Box 107, Folder 1-11)
    Includes annotated manuscript "The Tragedy of John Ury" by W.F. Prince (submitted by Harvey B. Marks); appeal by Christine Maura for N-YHS support of her efforts to encourage the city clergy to preach against lynchings, accompanied by communications on the subject with the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (the Executive Committee defines the matter as outside its scope of activities); correspondence with Walter G. Davis of the Maine Historical Society on defining and narrowing the scope of their collecting policies. Correspondents: George Caston Martin, H.N.W. Magill, Frederick C. Mather, Arthur H. Masten, Maiden Lane Historical Society, organizations based in Maryland and Massacusetts. Subjects: Mrs. Van Rensselaer.
  - Correspondence 1908-1926. Massachusetts Historical Society (3 folders) (Box 108, Folder 1-3)